A Guide to the Randolph M. Loughborough Papers, 1904-1967 [bulk 1938-1967]
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Randolph M. Loughborough Papers, 1904-1967 [bulk 1938-1967]
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 06-58
.5 linear feet, 1 box
The Randolph M. Lougborough Papers consists of .5 linear feet and spans the years 1904-1967. The Papers consists of correspondence; memorandum; applications; research; notes; news clippings; and articles.
Loughborough, Randolph McGill (1892-1970)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Unknown
Historical and Biographical Information
Randolph McGill Loughborough was born in Leesburg, Virginia on February 15, 1892. He was the son of Augustine Loughborough and Caroline Virginia Fauntleroy Loughborough, and a descendent of Captain Henry Fauntleroy who fought and died in the Revolutionary War. He attended private and public schools in Leesburg and Washington D.C. and went on to study textiles in Boston, Massachusetts with the Winslow Company and American Felt.
After a stint in the U.S. Navy during World War I as a Chief Gunners Mate, Loughborough worked for the Post Glover Company in Cincinnati, Ohio. His long career with Fairfax County began in 1924 as Assistant to County Engineer. In 1932 Loughborough was appointed County Purchasing Agent and during World War II acted as Coordinator of Civil Defense for Fairfax County. In 1945, he became Executive Secretary for Fairfax County.
On November 5, 1950, Fairfax County voters approved a referendum that would replace the current government with the county executive form in 1952. Shortly before the transition, the incoming Board of Supervisors named Loughborough, the current executive secretary, as the interim county executive for 60 days until they appointed a permanent one. On January 1, 1952, the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors held their first meeting under the county executive form and named Cartlon C. Massey as the permanent county executive, who assumed that role in March 1952. Loughborough finished his career as Head of Purchasing Division which included all purchases for Fairfax County Public Schools. He retired from the county in 1964.
Throughout his career Loughborough involved himself in numerous local community organizations. He acted as a Vestryman of Truro Episcopal Church in Fairfax, Treasurer of the Fairfax County Community Chest and board member of Fairfax Hospital. His membership to organizations included the National Institute of Governmental Purchasing; League of Virginia Counties; State Chamber of Commerce; Society of the Cincinnati; The International City Managers’ Association; and the Court House County Club of Fairfax, Virginia.
Loughborough married Getrude L. Savage of Norfolk, Virginia on March 6, 1936 and had two children Stuart Randolph and Minna Fauntleroy. He died September 10, 1970 at the Iliff Nursing Home in Dunn Loring after a long illness and is buried in Fairfax Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Biographical, 1938-1963
This series contains biographical information pertaining to Randolph Loughborough and research on his family’s history. Items include Loughborough’s fire insurance policy; application to the Society of the Cincinnati in the State of Virginia; news clippings; and photocopies of his ancestors’ vital records. Subjects include the Fauntleroy family; Henry Fauntleroy; and the Loughborough House in Georgetown.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1945-1967
This series consists of correspondence with Randolph Loughborough. It contains handwritten and typed letters. Subjects include the 1940s addition to the Historic Fairfax Court House; Bellafonte research in the Alexandria area; the Robeson Cutlery company; and various private and business matters.
Series 3: Fairfax County, 1935-1966
Sub-Series 3-1: Employment, 1935-1966
This series consists of materials relating to Loughborough’s long time employment with Fairfax County. Items include memorandum; budget materials; and various paperwork. Subjects include 1935 budget statistics for Fairfax County including information on the area’s colored schools and road history; a Department of Assessments letter to Fairfax County resident Myrtle Townes Taylor; Blanche Maxwell Melvin’s 1936 application to the Fairfax County Board of Education; a memo entitled “Going Into Business - Fairfax County”; and a fragmented memo from the county executive on Employees Group Life Insurance.
Sub-Series 3-2: Fairfax Courthouse Portraits Research, N.D.
This series contains materials pertaining to Loughborough’s research on the portrait collection at the Historic Fairfax Courthouse. Items include typed and handwritten research notes and a notepad containing research notes and correspondence drafts. Subjects include James R. Allison; R. Walton Moore; Walter Jones.
Series 4: Periodicals, 1904-1966
This series contains miscellaneous news clippings; articles; pamphlets; and a magazine that were in the files of Randolph Loughbrough. Subjects include health articles about gout and other afflictions; The Outlook journal article about Robert Lewis Dabnet; information about the Matthew B. Brady Civil War photograph collection; Grant Printing of Maryland; Garrett & Massie, Inc. Publishers; E.B. Adams Co.; Russell Harrington Cutler Col; Virginia Cavalcade magazine.
Arrangement
Organized chronologically and by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bio File - Randolph M. Loughborough
Photographic Archive of Fairfax County, Virginia - The Portrait Collection
None
Index Terms
Allison, James R.; Bellafonte, Pennsylvania; Carneal and Johnston, Architects; Fairfax County Board of Education; Fairfax County Budget; Fairfax County Colored Schools; Fairfax County Department of Assessments; Fairfax County Office of County Executive; Fairfax County Roads; Fauntleroy family; Fauntleroy, Caroline Virginia; Fauntleroy, Edward; Fauntleroy, Henry; Fauntleroy, Dr. John Fouchee; Fauntleroy, Joseph; Fauntleroy, Lavinia; Fauntleroy, William; Historic Fairfax County Courthouse; Jones, Walter; Kinnier, Henry; Larkin, Eleanor; Loughborough family; Loughborough, Augustine; Loughborough, Randolph; Loughborough, Louise; MacKay-Smith, A.; Manchester, Hugh; Melvin, Blanche Maxwell; Moore, R. Walton; Mulford, Edith Loughborough; Robeson Cutlery Company; Taylor, Myrtle Townes; Turner, Lavinia Beverley; Washington, Rev. Jaquelin M.
Container List
- Series 1: Biographical, 1938-1963
  - Hartford Fire Insurance Company Policy for Randolph Loughborough, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Application for Membership. The Society of the Cincinnati State of Virginia, 1959 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fauntleroy Family Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - “Old Uncle Dan The Old Time Slave” written for Mrs. A. Loughborough by her mother, Mrs. J.F. Fauntleroy, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - News clipping. The Washington Star. Junior League of Washington Moves to Loughborough House, 1963 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1945-1967
  - Letter. Carneal and Johnston, Architects to Phillip Stern. Re: Additions Fairfax Court House, 1945 November 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter. Edith Loughborough Mulford to Louise Loughborough, 1957 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter. Edward H. Fauntleroy and family to R.M. Loughborough, 1965 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter. Hugh Manchester, editor, The Centre Democrat to R.M. Loughborough. Re: Bellefonte, 1965 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter. Hugh Manchester, editor, The Centre Democrat to R.M. Loughborough. Re: Bellefonte, 1965 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter. Elenaor Larkin to R.M. Loughborough, 1965 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter. Elenaor Larkin to R.M. Loughborough, 1965 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter. Henry Kinner to R.M. Loughborough, 1966 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter. R.M. Loughborough to A. Mackay-Smith, 1967 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters. R.M. Loughborough with Robeson Cutlery Company, 1967 February (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter. R.M. Loughborough to Rev. Jaquelin M. Washington, 1967 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 3: Fairfax County, 1935-1966
  - Sub-Series 3-1: Employment, 1935-1966
    - Fairfax County Budget - Roads and Colored Schools, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Application to Fairfax County Board of Education. Blanche Maxwell Melvin, 1936 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Memorandum. Office of County Executive. Employees Group Life Insurance [fragment], 1965 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Fairfax County Department of Assessments concerning Myrtle Townes Taylor, 1966 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Going Into Business - Fairfax County, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sub-Series 3-2: Fairfax Courthouse Portraits Research, Undated.
    - Fairfax Court House Portraits - List and Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - James R. Allison #86 (1864-1927), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - R. Walton Moore #89 (1859-1941), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Walter Jones #95 (1776-1861), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Legal Pad. Contains notes and correspondence concerning Portrait Collection, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series 4: Publications, 1904-1966
  - “Old Virginia Society” by Emilie W. McVea. The Outlook, 1904 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Virginia Cavalcade Volume XV Number 1 Summer 1965, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - News clipping. “How to Keep Well” by Dr. Theodore R. Van Dellen. “Gout”, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous news clippings and pamphlets, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)